<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prerogative anatomized: or, An exact examination of those protestations and professions, whereby she hath attempted and indeavoured to preferre her selfe above the Parliament. By a lover of truth, peace and parliaments. Multa videntur quæ non sunt. Published by authority.</title>
            <author>Lover of truth, peace, and parliaments.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90938</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E20_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2844</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872201</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872201</idno>
            <idno type="VID">130866</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90938)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 130866)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 4:E20[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prerogative anatomized: or, An exact examination of those protestations and professions, whereby she hath attempted and indeavoured to preferre her selfe above the Parliament. By a lover of truth, peace and parliaments. Multa videntur quæ non sunt. Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>Lover of truth, peace, and parliaments.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wright, in the Old-Baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:130866:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PREROGATIVE Anatomized: OR, AN EXACT EXAMINATION Of thoſe Proteſtations and Profeſsions, whereby ſhe hath attempted and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to preferre her ſelfe above the PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>By a Lover of Truth, Peace, and Parliaments.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JOHN 7.24.</bibl>
               <p>Judge not according to the appearance, but judge righteous judgement.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Multa videntur quae non ſunt.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>John Wright,</hi> in the Old-Baily. 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:130866:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:130866:2"/>
            <head>PREROGATIVE ANATOMIZED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Diſputes between the King and Parliament are ſo high, the Declarations ſo numerous, the Prerogative-Proteſtations, and Pretences ſo plauſible, though tending to publike deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the Parliament proceedings ſo ſlow, ſo chargeable, ſo new, though juſt, no Parliament heretofore having power, or opportunitie, to maintaine the Kingdomes Rights, (the rod of diſſolution being perpetually held over them) that the amazed People ſtand betwixt the King and Parliament, like the ſillie Popiſh Prieſt between the bleſſed Virgin and our Saviour Chriſt, and know not which way to turn them, or whence to expect their ſalvation: I think it fit therefore to take the liberty of this ſcribling age, in ſetting down my ſenſe of Prerogative, that the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved people underſtanding the nature and end of it, may ſee the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that lies upon them, now or never to lay hold upon this their day, to un-inſlave their ſoules, perſons and eſtates, from Eccleſiaſticall and Prerogative tyrannie, by means of this preſent Parliament, ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully given and preſerved to us by the divine providence and mercy. Prerogative therefore, in the native, proper, and originall acception and intention of it, is nothing elſe, but a neceſſarie, juſt, and innocent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation of the Prince, to ſuch a proportion of ſplendour, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and authoritie, as may inable him, without incroa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hment to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:130866:3"/>ballance the other two Eſtates, and beare himſelfe in all things anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable unto his Office: for, they exceeding in number, were to add weight to him, to make a flouriſhing and ſweet compliance: but as it is diſtinguiſhed from the onely end and bound of true Regality, (the good of the people) is a tyrannicall power, deſtructive to Religion, Property, and Liberty, yea and to Regality it ſelfe, by narrowing and ſhrinking up the heart of a publike perſon, to ſelfe-will, ends, and aimes.</p>
            <p>The truth of this deſcription is evidenced, by the miſerable fruits of Prerogative before the Parliament, which are now generally knowne, though not generally acknowledged: our Religion was over-grown with ſuperſtition and profaneneſſe, Popiſh opinions were publikely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended in the Vniverſities, and preached in Pulpits, Popes Nuntio's admitted into the Kingdome, Covents of Friers erected, publike Maſſe telerated, preaching, pictie, godly Preachers ſuppreſt, ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, baniſhed: As for our Property and Liberty, they were quite loſt, and all the grievances that were ſingly introduced in the times of our predeceſſours, did joyntly, like a deluge, overwhelme us. For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe of theſe preſſures was this Parliament called, and cri'd up by the People, I feare, with as much, too much confidence in it, as the Jewes of old had in the Temple of the Lord, when they cried, <hi>Templum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, Templum Domini,</hi> and in the mean time rebelled againſt the God of the Temple; and for this ſin, amongſt others, I doubt, the peace made with Scotland proves but a change of our adverſaries, from them, to our ſelves: And yet, though the continuance of our miſerie be very grievous, in my judgment, the ſtate of the warre is much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then it was, before the Parliament: For, now (whatſoever pretences are made) we conflict with our true enemie, the Popiſh par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and their adherents; whereas before we ſhould have beene led hood wink'd for the ſervice of our enemies, mutually to deſtroy our ſelves, and our Proteſtant Friends: And, me thinks, in this very thing, which drawes the greateſt <hi>odium</hi> upon the Parliament, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve infinite commendations, that ſince they could not keep off a war from the Kingdome, they occaſioned this happy divertion. Yet hence the people complaine, we hoped for help from the Parliament, and we are now in worſe condition then we were before. So it fared with the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after <hi>Moſes</hi> appeared for their deliverance: their task was doubled, and <hi>Moſes</hi> their deliverer is charged by them, to have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:130866:3"/>put a ſword into the hands of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to ſlay them. Thus all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills that by the adverſaries of the Parliament have been miſchievouſly multiplied, to hinder Reformation, are unjuſtly laid upon the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and thus God is diſhonoured every way: for, when hopes of deliverance firſt appeare, we idolize the meanes; and when our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance proves not ſo ſudden, nor ſo eaſie as we expect, then we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the meanes. By Gods goodneſſe, for his own glory, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath appeared, as it is, an arme of fleſh, unable to ſave; and yet by the ſame goodneſſe, the major part continues faithfull to him and the Kingdome, and God hath not left it without glorious teſtimony of his aſſiſtance, and good aſſurance to us, that God will give us the like ſucceſſe he gave our Brethren the Scots, if we would yet follow their zeale, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> glory, and their unity amongſt themſelves; neither is it altogether to be contemned, that which is already effected by this Parliament: the Popiſh and Prelaticall party are wholly diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced, and reſolutely oppoſed, by the Parliament, by whom faithfull Miniſters are incouraged, and the purity of the Goſpell maintained, and ſuch Lawes paſt, for the vindication of Property and Liberty, as better cannot be deviſed: and now the Scales are quite turn'd, Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative pleads nothing but Law, and conſcience; Papiſts and Prelates defend the Proteſtant Religion, Delinquents the Law and Parliament: And the Parliament, cleane contrary, deſtroyes Religion, Property, King, Parliament, and Kingdome: and in a word, the Lion is turn'd Lamb, and the Lamb is turn'd Lion. But this is no new thing, we have an example of the firſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>He lieth in wait ſecretly, as a Lion in his den, he crowcheth, and humbleth himſelfe, that the poore may fall by his ſtrong ones.</hi> Whatſoever pretence the Lion makes of humility, his end is to devoure.</p>
            <p>For the other, we know there is no juſter indignation then that which proceeds from patience abus'd, or love contemn'd; the meekeſt man upon the earth, will be kindled into rage, when an Idoll ſtands in competition with the God of all glory; or when the being of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Church of God are both indangered; in ſuch a caſe as this, <hi>Moſes</hi> tries what partie he can make in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and commands them every one to ſlay his brother: if God or good men, cauſe any to be troubled, it is of very faithfullneſſe, and for their good. But here it is objected: what danger is our Religion, Property, or Libertie in?</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Prerogative will defend the true Proteſtant Profeſſion, as it was in the dayes of Q.</hi> Elizabeth,</item>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:130866:4"/>
               <item>2 <hi>It will defend the Property, and Liberty of the People, according the old and new Lawes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>It will defend the juſt Power and Priviledge of Parliament.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To the firſt: <hi>Prerogative will defend the true Proteſtant Religion, as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as in the dayes of Queene</hi> Elizabeth. How good a defender of the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oteſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Religion Prerogative was before the Parliament, you had a little Breviat at the beginning, and how good a defence ſhe is like to make for the future, we ſee by the inſtruments ſhe chuſeth to defend it; Papiſts, Enemies, and Prelates, Travtors to Religion: but her ſolemn Proteſtations muſt be believed. Well then, let us admit the utmoſt of thoſe Proteſtations, and the reſult is this; The ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the ſame Eccleſiaſticall Government, that was in the daies of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> is that pitch of Reformation, which Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive will conſent to, and maintaine, but one jot further it will not go; and why ſhould not this content the Parliament, as well as the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? were not the times of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the happieſt that ever England ſaw? To this the parliament, and all good men, anſwer, that in the heginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> reigne, ſhe choſe ſuch men to be Biſhops (for the moſt part) as had ſuffered perſecution for the telamonie of the Goſpell in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, and by ſuch ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings had, both evidenced their fidelity to <hi>Chriſt</hi> their Maſter, and learnt compaſſion toward the Church their Brethren: the ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Biſhops were ſomthing worſe, but civill authority was then ſo active to ſuppreſſe Popery, and incourage good Miniſters, to do their duty, that a ſlender and inſufficient Eccleſiaſticall Government might not be much taken notice of: but now we have a Popiſh Queene, that hath a great influence into the Civill State; we have (for the moſt part) a diſſolute, and degenerate Clergy, that hath once already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed and perſecuted Religion, and yet now we muſt have no better guard for Religion, then the not unchaſt, becauſe untempted Prelacy, in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> It's hard uſage, becauſe I need not any cloake when the Sun ſhines, to keep it from me in a ſtorme: or, becauſe in time of peace, I walke unarm'd, to put me naked in the front of a Battell: ſurely in this (which is the greateſt matter of all others) the Parliament is to be juſtified, that they ſeeke another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of defence for Religion now, then in the daies of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth:</hi> and in that they ſet not any times, or perſons, to be a ſtandard of Reformation, but the Word of God, which is, and ought to be the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:130866:4"/>rule of all Reformation of the Church, both in Doctrine and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: and this I ſuppoſe is ſatisfactory to the firſt: we will proceed to weigh the two other promiſes of Prerogative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It will defend the Propertie and Libertie of the People, according to the old and new Lawes, and it will defend the juſt Priviledge of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſatisfie for this, we muſt alwaies direct our eyes, and fix them upon Prerogatives ſelfe, by conſidering what ſhe is by nature, rather then what ſhe ſpeakes by art; and to diſcover the nature of Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, we muſt conſider what her conſtant actions are, how ſhe carries her ſelfe, when her motions proceed only from her own internall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, when ſhe is a free agent, without any interpoſition of true neceſſity, feare, or danger; for then, and then onely, ſhe acts her ſelfe: and how can you have a better and fuller diſcovery of her diſpoſition, then by her conſtant courſe of proceedings, before this Parliament, ſet downe at large, in the Parliaments Remonſtrance of the State of the Kingdome: for the keeping of which from the peoples view, there was ſo ſtrong a partie made in the Houſe of Commons (conſiſting, as we may well ſuppoſe, of that Prerogative-party which have now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted that Houſe) that the debate of publiſhing it was two ſeverall times protracted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill midnight, the reſolution curried but by 11. voices, and the printing of it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> proteſted againſt; ſo dangerous a thing was it counted, to let the people underſtand their danger, and ſee the evills intended, leſt the ſhould look out for redreſſe, and indeavour for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; nothing could be more contrary to the deſignes of Prerogative, who had formerly blinded their eys by ſuppreſſing preaching, and the Law; and Found their ſtands, by taking away Property &amp; Liberty, that thus blind fold and bound, they might be carried at pleaſure by their ſtand leaders, till both fell into the ditch. This opening the eys of the blind, was the ſedition and faction of Parliaments; for this, after their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſſolutions, they were alwaies charged to be led by a few dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly affected perſons, peſts and vipers: and for this they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, becauſe they alſo would not become a grievance, by giving mony in the firſt place, with out redreſſe or ſpeech of their grievances.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the nature of Prerogative: but it is anſwered, that the unparallel'd Acts of grace granted this Parliament, may juſtly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, not onely oblivion of theſe things paſt, but confidence for the time to come, that the very nature and judgement of Prerogative is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:130866:5"/>changed. From the good Laws granted this Parliament, this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion followes verie naturally, that it is happie for the Kingdome when the King concurs with the adviſe of his Parliament, but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it will hardly follow from thence, that Prerogative is regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, there was ſomthing in the ballance of thoſe gracious Grants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides good nature: the preſence of the Scotch Army which caus'd this Parliament, made it act more vigorouſly whilſt it was here, then other Parliaments, but that Army being returned, and the Kingdome of Scotland ſetled, it was conceiv'd that the tame Kingdome of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, which only <hi>Per Antiperiſtaſin,</hi> had received a little heate from the North would quickly coole again, and be reduc'd to its former mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leableneſſe. For the better effecting whereof Prerogatives firſt act was, notwithſtanding the rebellion in Ireland and the juſt feare of Popiſh Aſſaſinates, to diſcharge the Guard of the Parliament, and when they petitioned to have their Guard againe, one was ſet upon them under a Commander they could not confide in, ſo they choſe rather to bee without. The next act of Prerogative was, to deſtroy the whole Parliament, by breaking the bundle, ſticke after ſticke, and this was attempted by an aſſault made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Houſe of Commons, with an intent forcibly to have ſeized ſome of their Members, under the pretence of an accuſation of high Treaſon, which was ſo much reſented by the Kingdome, that all the Counties of England, though it neceſſary by numerous Petitions to preſent the pledges of their publick affections to the Parliament, and to declare their unanimous reſolutions, to maintaine their Priviledges, amongſt which well-affected people, very many that were neere hand, appeared in good numbers, voluntarily to guard the Parliament, ſome of them with all importunity, crying for Juſtice, and againſt Biſhops, which laſt generall diſcontent occaſioned the paſſing ſome more good Laws for publick ſatisfaction, though now, that Ebulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of publike affection is the pretended cauſe of all our miſery, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of tumults, which are ſo mightily declaim'd againſt, and ſo continually complain'd of by Prerogative, who was contented to whip the Kingdome till it cri'd, and now makes that crying, a maine argument of deſerting the Parliament, and of bringing open force to deſtroy that, and the Kingdome: and indeed Prerogative had good reaſon to be incens'd againſt theſe officious Aſſemblies; for thereby not only all her deſignes were made abortive, but all hopes of effecting
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:130866:5"/>any thing againſt the Parliament, in the Southern parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome wholly fruſtrate; therefore ſhe muſt retire to a place of ſtrength, where her ſervants (Fugitives and Traytors to the Parliament, and Kingdome,) may be avow'd and protected: and then, for the better effecting a diviſion in the Kingdome, Prerogative begins to withdraw her partie from the Parliament; ſome by eſpeciall Letters upon their Allegiance, others for feare of being put out of their Offices and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, under His Majeſty. In a word, all the trees were wind-ſhaken, and thoſe that were not faſt rooted, fell; who though they had ſtood out all the tumults, without danger or hazard, yet two moneths after they muſt withdraw themſelves from the Parliament, as Prerogative ſaith, for feare of tumults, though themſelves being ſummoned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and give their attendance (according to their dutie) in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, alledge only His Majeſties command for their abſence. After this a journey is pretended into Ireland, that an Army may be rais'd with leſſe ſuſpition: then His Majeſty (that, in the greateſt heat of diſcontent, went through London hunted at New-market; paſt through the whole Kingdome, ſecure and dangerleſſe alone,) in the midſt of that dutifull Country of Yorkeſhire, propoſed as a patterne of affection and loyalty to the Kingdome, muſt have a guard, which now (by the aſſiſtance of Papiſts and Delinquents, at home, and by meanes of forraigne ſupplies from abroad) is growne a royall Army, not only avowing His Majeſties Servants, but open warre, againſt that trayterous Faction in both Houſes of Parliament; and yet His Majeſties ſoule abhorres the very thought of warre againſt his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet the Parliament are now declared abettors of that Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, againſt which the warre is maintained, and nothing, that will or malice can deviſe, held bad enough, ſufficiently to aſperſe and blaſt their proceedings.</p>
            <p>Now after all this, he that can think Prerogatives nature changed, becauſe of a few good words, and faire Proteſtations, let him think ſo; and he that will be deceived, let him be deceived; but <hi>wiſdome is juſtified of her children:</hi> in vain ſhall we expect <hi>figs of thornes, or grapes of thiſtles;</hi> ſuch as the tree is, ſuch the fruit will be. Yet ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that Prerogative ſhould really intend to performe her Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ingagements to the Kingdome, when this preſent Faction of both Houſes of Parliament is ſubdued; though no man ought to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion His Majeſties perſonall goodneſſe, yet no man can doubt, but that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:130866:6"/>this Army, thus compoſed, when it hath maſtered the Parliament, will alſo give Law to His Majeſty, as the Roman Army did to the Emperours, after the conqueſt of the Empire: and then, the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not, Whether we will truſt His Majeſty? which no man will queſtion; but whether we will ſubject our ſelves, with the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, and beſt deſerving Parliament that ever was, to Papiſts and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents?</p>
            <p>But here it is objected:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Parliament is as juſtly to be blamed, and there lie as cleere and manifold Objections againſt it, as againſt Prerogative.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>It endeavours unneceſſarily to perpetuate it ſelfe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>It ſeekes the alteration of the ancient frame of Government, and the abolition of the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>It deſtroyes Property and Liberty, as much as ever Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive did.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>They are ſeduced by a few factious Members, who are wholly tranſported with private ends and aimes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>They ſeek the ruine of the King and his Poſterity.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To the firſt: <hi>This Parliament endeavours to perpetuate it ſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſarily. Anſw.</hi> I do not wonder that Prerogative is impatient of this check, and that it endeavours therefore to cut this Gordian knot, it cannot untie: but why the Parliament ſhould not be infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more deſirous to be diſſolv'd, then continue, if the Religion, peace, and proſperity of the Kingdome were once throughly ſetled, no wiſe man can give a reaſon.</p>
            <p>The Prelaticall Party proclaime every where, That if the Revenue of the Church be taken away (which is all they feare, though no man endeavours it) Religion and Learning will utterly decay; their very godlineſſe will not ſtand without gaine: and why the Parliament ſhould be ſo much in love with a gainleſſe unceſſant labour, I cannot deviſe. Oh, but every man is ambitious of power. Truly, power in a multitude, where all equally beare the burden, (but the moſt active carrie the moſt honour) will never be valued by the major part, whoſe private intereſts, and care of their family and eſtates, is nearer and dearer to them, then any other thing whatſoever, after their ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall be diſcharged to God and the publike. And therefore that the deſired diſſolution of this Parliament might be effected, it were much the readier way, to endeavour the ſetling the diſtractions of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:130866:6"/>Kingdome, then by multiplying the dangers, to neceſſitate the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>But to the ſecond Objection: <hi>The Parliament ſeeks the alteration of the ancient frame of government, and the abolition of the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes of this Kingdome. Anſw.</hi> Of the Eccleſiaſticall Laws and Government it doth, for the reaſons given before; and becauſe it ought to obey God rather then man: but for the authority of the civill Magiſtrate, and the common Law and Juſtice of the Kingdome, it hath alwayes conformed to them, having never endeavoured any thing without the Kings conſent, but only to preſerve it ſelfe and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in ſuch a caſe: and I doubt not, but this Poſition of theirs will be found very legall, <hi>That the Kings Authority, ſignified by his Courts, (eſpecially by the high Court of Parliament, the repreſentative Body of the Kingdom) is more obligatory to the Kingdom, then his perſonall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, out of his Courts, though his perſonall Commands are alwayes to be reverenced, when they contradict not thoſe Courts, and the Law:</hi> and therefore I aſſure my ſelfe, in concluſion, the loyalty and duty of the Parliament, and of that part of the Kingdome which obeyes the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, will be found unblemiſht.</p>
            <p>But to the third Objection: <hi>The Parliament invades the Property and Liberty of the Subject, as much as ever Prerogative did. An.</hi> When I conſider, how often, and with how much art Prerogative inculcates this to the people, pretending great affection to them, and much care of their ſufferings, together with much diſpleaſure againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for their oppreſſion; I look upon this as the maine deſigne of Prerogative, to multiply the dangers and miſeries of the Kingdome, thereby neceſſitating the Parliament to lay exceſſive charges upon the people, that the preſent ſenſe of evills, which alwayes make deepeſt impreſſions in mens minds, might induce the people, whoſe love lies moſt in their purſes, to deſert the Parliament; but the wiſe will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that the ſearching of a deep wound is more painfull then the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it: yet he that ſearcheth my wound, to cure me, is more my friend, then he that makes it, onely to abuſe me, and pleaſe himſelfe. This is the true ſtate of the caſe: Prerogative oppreſt the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Parliament, for her own pleaſure, without any neceſſity, and laid the foundation of theſe preſent evills; the Parliament, at the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire of the people, undertake the cure: and, whileſt they might operate without interruption, proceeded in the work, though with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:130866:7"/>much difficulty and charge, yet with much good ſucceſſe, and generall ſatisfaction; ſetling peace with Scotland, and good Laws in England. But the Jeſuitiſh Adverſary, fearing, thereby, our happineſſe, and their own ruine, ſtirre up that cruell and univerſall rebellion in Ireland, which might very well put the Parliament into Feares and Jealouſies, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them expect whatſoeuer the malice of hell could inſpire into their rage and fury, who in cold bloud could contrive a powder-plot. Yet for all this, the Parliament could not obtaine a Guard, but inſtead of that, hath been aſſaulted, and purſued, with thoſe continuall miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and wicked plots before recited. And now for the Parliaments taxing the Kingdome, to the twentieth part of their eſtates, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning thoſe that oppoſe, is there not a cauſe? a juſt, a manifeſt, and a neceſſary cauſe for it? ſhall this be cal'd deſtruction of property and liberty? If the Parliament, intruſted for that purpoſe, may not imploy the eſtates and perſons of the Kingdome, for the neceſſary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of it ſelfe; then let it be the wiſdome of the Kingdome, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve themſelves a fat, full, and eaſie prey for their enemies, but by no meanes to preſerve themſelves from their enemies: Let the Phyſitian cure his patients, but let not them obſerve the preſcriptions and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Phyſitian: let ill humours be purged, but let not the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be weakened: put any impoſſibilities upon the Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; let them be accuſed of infidelity, if they doe not their beſt to deliver us: and let them be accuſed of oppreſſion, if they do their beſt to deliver us. The Parliament hath a very happy time of it to ſerve ſuch humours, and receive ſuch incouragements: but the bleſſing of the Saints on earth is upon them, their way is with God, and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in heaven. As for thoſe that repine at this charge, Sodome and Gomorrah, Rome and Antichriſt, at the laſt day ſhall riſe up in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them, and ſhall condemne them. For, the Popiſh party ſpare for no coſt, ſtick at no danger, venture all, both eſtates and life, for the Catholike cauſe: but we had rather our Religion, and all that's deare unto us, ſhould be ſubmitted to their cruell mercy, then contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the twentieth part of our eſtates for our own deliverance. And thus much for the third Objection.</p>
            <p>For the fourth: <hi>Their factious leaders are carried with private ends and aimes. Anſ.</hi> Certainly, whatſoever their ends are, they that accuſe them, are not ſo much of their counſell, as to know their ends; and as ſure it is; they might have attain'd their private aimes, (if they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:130866:7"/>have any) much more ſpeedily, by deſerting the publick, as others have done, then by adhering to it, as they doe: but whatſoever their ends and aimes be, we will leave that to God and their own conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; let their ends be what they will, the Houſes of Parliament have no relations to them, or dependence upon them, that they ſhould ſerve their ends, if at any time they conſent to their opinion; they are convinc'd by publike reaſons, and it very well beſeems the honour of a Parliament, that he who ſpeakes moſt reaſon, ſhould rule the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: I never heard that it was any diſparagement, to the Apoſtles, and Church aſſembled in the firſt Synod, that they all ſubmitted to the ſentence of S. <hi>James,</hi> and out of his opinion fram'd the firſt Canons of the Church.</p>
            <p>The fifth objection is, <hi>They ſeeke the ruine and deſtruction of the King and his Poſterity.</hi> To that the Parliament anſwers, That the force they imploy, to recover him and his children againe out of the hands of thoſe wicked Counſellours; who have ſeduced him away from his Parliament and Kingdome, is a ſervice to the King; as dutifull and loving, as it would be to indeavour the redemption of him by force, if he and his children were taken priſoners by Turkiſh Pirats, and detain'd by force. And for the hazard of His Majeſties Perſon, and his Princely Children at Keinton Battell, had it been in the power of the Parliaments forces to have kept them out of the danger of that Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, as it was in the power of that Army about the King, they would not have ſuffered him or his children to have ventured an haire of their heads. But perhaps the leaders of that Army will ſay, the Kings reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions were ſo ſtrongly ſet, and his commands ſo peremptory, that they could not keep him from the Battell. Fidelity never made ſuch a plea. To compell the King for his ſafety, is more loyaltie, then to obey him for his deſtruction: therefore the danger of the Kings life, that day, and of his childrens, let it lie (as it ought) upon that deſtructive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obedient Army, which might have kept them from that hazard, and would not.</p>
            <p>But it is objected further:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Houſes of Parliament are favourers of Browniſts and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>They have promiſed the Papiſts to repeale all the Laws-eſtabliſhed againſt them, if they will joyne on their ſide.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Their reformation, will be a deformation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:130866:8"/>
                  <item>4. <hi>They reject the Booke of Common Prayer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>They differ ſo much amongſt themſelves, that if they had their own minds, they know not what they would have.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Objections are with ſo much art and cunning interweav'd in the ſeverall Declarations and Libells of the Prerogative-partie, and with ſo much confidence affirm'd, that a man who knowes aſſuredly the contrary, muſt have a good reſolution, if he be not out-faced in his own knowledge: yet take theſe Objections nakedly, as they are ſum'd up here together: how contradictory are they in themſelves? how impoſſible ſome of them, how ſcandalous all? the very likelieſt of them bare ſurmiſes, and propheticall conjectures: nevertheleſſe let the people be inſnar'd by them and it is enough. But certainly, if the Prerogative pen-men did themſelves believe them, they would put it to an iſſue, by procuring the Parliament their deſired Synod, and then it would evidently appeare, what the perſons are the Parliament affects, what opinions they incline to, and what reformation they intend. But I feare their conſciences miſgive them; the womb of this intended birth being declar'd to be the Word of God, the fruit can be nothing but the childe of truth, and therefore the ſureſt way is to hinder the birth, and in the mean time make the people believe, the Parliament is in labour of a Moon-Calfe. But the Houſes declare their intentions cleerly enough, to ſatisfie any honeſt man.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 They ſay it is ſafer for Religion, that we concurre with other Proteſtant Churches in point of Diſcipline, then with the Papiſts, and it will beget a ſtronger mutuall confidence between us and them.</item>
               <item>2 They do and have declared againſt the preſſing of indifferent Ceremonies, (though eſtabiſhed by Law) upon weake conſciences. And hereby let all the world judge, whether their proceedings in all theſe things, be not pious, and moderate, and ſuch as may be expected, from the repreſentative Body of the Kindome of England.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And now, O England, why halteſt thou between two opinions? If Prerogative be turn'd thy friend, cleave to Prerogative: if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament be turn'd thy enemy, deſert the Parliament: nothing will ſooner deſtroy thee, then this thy neutrality. I have declared unto thee my ſenſe of both: the judgement is thine, reſolve wiſely and ſpeedily: which ſoever thou chooſeſt, it is either life, or death; God direct thee in thy choice, as may be moſt for his glory: for my part, I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:130866:8"/>think the Parliament may juſtly take up this inſuing complaint, againſt all thoſe that withdraw their confidence from them.</p>
            <p>Parl. <hi>We have forſaken father and mother, wife and children, houſes and lands, for the Gospells ſake and yours; we daily ſpend our ſelves, decay our healths, venture our lives, for your ſervice: for your ſakes we have walked craggie paths, and not beene wearied: the Lion hath roared againſt us, and we have not been terrified: mountaines of oppoſition have beene heaped one upon another, in our way, like</hi> Pelion <hi>upon</hi> Oſſa, <hi>and we have not beene diſcouraged. For your ſakes we are curs'd, reproach'd, kill'd all the day long, and yet for all this we complain not: That onely which breaks our heart is, that you, even you, for whom we have done and ſuffered all theſe things; that you, I ſay, ſhould grudge to aſſiſt us, murmure againſt us, revile and hats us. God knows, we deſire your good, as our owne ſoules, and all this unkindneſſe of yours is not ſufficient to turne our hearts from you, but we ſtand ſtill, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſpend, and be ſpent for you, though</hi> the more <hi>we</hi> love you, the leſſe we be belov'd of you: <hi>God knows, we have no other intention, but for your good, to take away the droſſe from the ſilver, Tradition from the Church, and wicked perſons from the King: that the Worſhip of God may be eſtabliſhed in purity, and the throne of the King in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; for the effecting whereof, we know no other way, but that. His Majeſty (according to his own Propoſition) follow the example of Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>not in maintaining Prelates, but in eſteeming Parliaments: She accounted them the Repreſentative Body of the Kingdome, not a Faction: She ſought their loves, not their lives: She called them often together, onely to ſee her good people, and to inquire of their grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that ſhe might redreſſe them, and when returne was made,</hi> Omnia bene, <hi>and then Subſidies given, ſhe refuſed their thank-offering, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> I ſeek not yours, but you. <hi>Then the bleſſing of God went along with the juſtice of the Prince, and the dutifull obedience of the People waited as a handmaid upon the eye of her Miſtris: The love of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments was that, and that onely (under God) which made the times of Q.</hi> Elizabeth <hi>happy: and the contempt of, and oppoſition againſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is that, and that onely, (the ſecret judgements of God for our ſinnes, being left to God) which is the viſible cauſe of all our miſeries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore O King and People, if ye deſire to attaine the happineſſe of bleſſed Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and her proſperous times, obſerve but this one precept, Confide in Parliaments.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
